<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Monte-Carlo on Luke Salamone&#39;s Blog</title>
    <link>https://lukesalamone.github.io/tags/monte-carlo/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Monte-Carlo on Luke Salamone&#39;s Blog</description>
    <generator>Hugo</generator>
    <language>en</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 21 Jul 2020 17:34:05 +0800</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="https://lukesalamone.github.io/tags/monte-carlo/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>What is the Hardest Hangman Word?</title>
      <link>https://lukesalamone.github.io/posts/hardest-hangman-word/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 21 Jul 2020 17:34:05 +0800</pubDate>
      <guid>https://lukesalamone.github.io/posts/hardest-hangman-word/</guid>
      <description>It seems like a simple enough question. Which word should you choose so that it takes your opponent the most guesses to discover it? Should you choose a long word to use up your opponent&amp;rsquo;s guesses? Or perhaps a short word with obscure letters? In this document I look into this question. But first, a bit of background.&#xA;If you&amp;rsquo;re not familiar with the rules of hangman, it is a guessing game played between two people.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Estimating Pi with a Monte Carlo Simulation</title>
      <link>https://lukesalamone.github.io/posts/monte-carlo/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 09 Jul 2020 15:40:14 +0800</pubDate>
      <guid>https://lukesalamone.github.io/posts/monte-carlo/</guid>
      <description>A Monte Carlo simulation is a method of estimating events or quantities which are difficult or computationally infeasible to derive a closed-form solution to. The value of the mathematical constant Pi is a good example of this: although it is possible to calculate the exact value of Pi, a good estimate is easily demonstrated with just a few lines of code.&#xA;Monte Carlo simulations work when the input can be drawn from a random probability distribution, and the outcome can be derived deterministically from the input.</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
