<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>chess on Luke Salamone&#39;s Blog</title>
    <link>https://lukesalamone.github.io/tags/chess/</link>
    <description>Recent content in chess on Luke Salamone&#39;s Blog</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <copyright>&lt;a href=&#34;https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;CC BY-NC 4.0&lt;/a&gt;</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Sat, 08 Oct 2022 15:17:36 -0700</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://lukesalamone.github.io/tags/chess/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>A new type of chess tournament</title>
      <link>https://lukesalamone.github.io/posts/qualitative-analysis-chess/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 08 Oct 2022 15:17:36 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://lukesalamone.github.io/posts/qualitative-analysis-chess/</guid>
      <description>This is part 2 of a paper I wrote for Ken Forbus&amp;rsquo; Qualitative Reasoning course, adapted for this blog. You can find a printable version of the paper here and part 1 here.
In the previous post I discussed the history of chess engines and why they don&amp;rsquo;t &amp;ldquo;think&amp;rdquo; like we think. Trading interpretability for computation cycles ultimately led to the engines we have today, fairly alien in nature and perhaps less pedagogically useful because of it.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Chess Engine&#39;s Final Horizon</title>
      <link>https://lukesalamone.github.io/posts/chess-engine-history/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 07 Oct 2022 20:17:21 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://lukesalamone.github.io/posts/chess-engine-history/</guid>
      <description>This is part 1 of a paper I wrote for Ken Forbus&amp;rsquo; Qualitative Reasoning course, adapted for this blog. You can find a printable version of the paper here and part 2 here.
Computers that play chess, otherwise known as chess engines, have existed since at least the late 1940s. Because the game was said to require the perfect combination of planning, strategy, psychology, and calculation, chess was once thought to be an activity directly correlated with intelligence, and that only a truly intelligent computer should be able to defeat humans.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>A Suboptimal Minimax</title>
      <link>https://lukesalamone.github.io/posts/a-suboptimal-minimax/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 02 Jul 2022 16:24:10 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://lukesalamone.github.io/posts/a-suboptimal-minimax/</guid>
      <description>MathJax.Hub.Config({ tex2jax: { inlineMath: [[&#39;$&#39;,&#39;$&#39;], [&#39;\\(&#39;,&#39;\\)&#39;]], displayMath: [[&#39;$$&#39;,&#39;$$&#39;], [&#39;\[&#39;,&#39;\]&#39;]], processEscapes: true, processEnvironments: true, skipTags: [&#39;script&#39;, &#39;noscript&#39;, &#39;style&#39;, &#39;textarea&#39;, &#39;pre&#39;], TeX: { equationNumbers: { autoNumber: &#34;AMS&#34; }, extensions: [&#34;AMSmath.js&#34;, &#34;AMSsymbols.js&#34;] } } });  MathJax.Hub.Queue(function() { var all = MathJax.Hub.getAllJax(), i; for(i = 0; i Minimax solves for optimal opponent play, minimizing the best move an opponent could make. But what if we relaxed this restriction, and instead assumed that an opponent will make moves according to some known policy function?</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Alphabet Chess</title>
      <link>https://lukesalamone.github.io/posts/alphabet-chess/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 10 Jun 2022 23:56:14 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://lukesalamone.github.io/posts/alphabet-chess/</guid>
      <description>Chess has been played in different forms since the seventh century, and in its modern form since the nineteenth century. Opening theory, i.e. the study of the best moves to begin the game with, has been developing since then.
The EGG Opening I was inspired the other day after watching a video by Eric Rosen called &amp;ldquo;Quadruple Egg&amp;rdquo;. Chess boards are usually notated from left to right with the letters A through H.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
