<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Explainability on Luke Salamone&#39;s Blog</title>
    <link>https://lukesalamone.github.io/tags/explainability/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Explainability on Luke Salamone&#39;s Blog</description>
    <generator>Hugo</generator>
    <language>en</language>
    <copyright>&lt;a href=&#34;https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;CC BY-NC 4.0&lt;/a&gt;</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 25 Aug 2023 20:47:30 -0800</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="https://lukesalamone.github.io/tags/explainability/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>What is a blunder in chess?</title>
      <link>https://lukesalamone.github.io/posts/chess-blunders/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 25 Aug 2023 20:47:30 -0800</pubDate>
      <guid>https://lukesalamone.github.io/posts/chess-blunders/</guid>
      <description>What is a blunder in chess? The tension between the qualitative and quantitative answers to this question are at the heart of the different approaches towards chess, and more broadly, how quantitative metrics may oversimplify, but qualitative metrics&#xA;Qualitative answer There are many qualitative answers to this question, especially when comparing &amp;ldquo;blunders&amp;rdquo; and &amp;ldquo;mistakes&amp;rdquo;:&#xA;&amp;ldquo;a move that negatively affects their position in a significant way&amp;rdquo; ~ chess.com &amp;ldquo;severely worsens the player&amp;rsquo;s situation by allowing a loss of material, checkmate, or anything similar&amp;rdquo; ~ Wikipedia &amp;ldquo;Blunders tend to be immediately refutable, while mistakes require planning to capitalize on.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The Chess Engine&#39;s Final Horizon</title>
      <link>https://lukesalamone.github.io/posts/chess-engine-history/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 07 Oct 2022 20:17:21 -0700</pubDate>
      <guid>https://lukesalamone.github.io/posts/chess-engine-history/</guid>
      <description>This is part 1 of a paper I wrote for Ken Forbus&amp;rsquo; Qualitative Reasoning course, adapted for this blog. You can find a printable version of the paper here and part 2 here.&#xA;Computers that play chess, otherwise known as chess engines, have existed since at least the late 1940s. Because the game was said to require the perfect combination of planning, strategy, psychology, and calculation, chess was once thought to be an activity directly correlated with intelligence, and that only a truly intelligent computer should be able to defeat humans.</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
